<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section id="ajaxdev">
 <title>Ajax client development</title>
 <para>
  Pazpar2 offers programmers a simple Web Service protocol that can be
  used (queried in a request/response fashion) from any, server- or
  client-side, programming language with an XML support. However, when
  programming a Web-based client to Pazpar2, to achieve certain level of
  interactivity and instant notification of latest changes in the result
  set, Ajax (Asynchronous JavaScript and XML) technology may be used. An
  Ajax client allows user to browse the results before the lengthy
  process of information retrieval from the back-end targets is
  finished. Blocking and waiting for usually slow back-end targets is
  one of the biggest functionality issues in a federated search engine.
 </para>
 <para>
  Pazpar2 comes with a small JavaScript library called
  <filename>pz2.js</filename>.
  This library is designed to simplify development of an Ajax-based pazpar2
  client and alleviate the programmer from the low-level details like
  polling the web service, fetching and parsing returned XML output or
  managing timers, sessions and basic state variables.
 </para>
 <para>
  The library supports most major browsers including Firefox 1.5+, IE
  6+, Safari 2+, Opera 9+ and Konqueror.
 </para>
 <para>
  The library can work in two modes: a session-aware mode and a
  session-less mode.
 </para>
 <para>
  In the session-aware mode, the library assumes that the pazpar2
  daemon is contacted directly (preferably via Apache proxy to avoid
  security breaches) and tracks the session IDs internally.
 </para>
 <para>
  In the session-less, mode the library assumes that the client is
  identified on the server and the session IDs are not managed
  directly. This way of operation requires a more sophisticated pazpar2
  proxy (preferably a wrapper written in a server-side scripting
  language like PHP that can identify clients and relate them to open
  pazpar2 sessions).
 </para>
 <para><bridgehead>Using <filename>pz2.js</filename></bridgehead></para>
 <para>
  Client development with the <filename>pz2.js</filename> is strongly event based and the
  style should be familiar to most JavaScript developers. A simple
  client (jsdemo) is distributed with Pazpar2's source code and shows
  how to set-up and use <filename>pz2.js</filename>.
 </para>
 <para>
  In short, the programmer starts by instantiating the pz2 object and
  passing an array of parameters to the constructor. The parameter array
  specifies callbacks used for handling responses to the pazpar2
  commands. Additionally, the parameter array is used to configure
  run-time parameters of the <filename>pz2.js</filename> like polling
  timer time-outs, session-mode and XSLT stylesheets.
 </para>
 <para><bridgehead>Command callbacks</bridgehead></para>
 <para>
  Callback naming is simple, and follows “on” prefix plus command name
  scheme (like onsearch, onshow, onrecord, ... etc.). When the programmer
  calls a function like show or record on the pz2 object, <filename>pz2.js</filename> will
  keep on polling pazpar2 (until the backend targets are idle) and with
  each command's response an assigned callback will be called. In case
  of Pazpar2's internal error, an error callback is called.
 </para>
 <screen>
  my_paz = new pz2 (
  {
   "pazpar2path": "/pazpar2/search.pz2",
   "usesessions" : true,

   // assigning command handler, turns on automatic polling
   "onshow": my_onshow,
   // polling period for each command can be specified
   "showtime": 500,

   "onterm": my_onterm,
   // facet terms are specified as a comma separated list
   "termlist": "subject,author",

   "onrecord": my_onrecord
  }
  );
 </screen>
 <para>
  Each command callback is a user-defined function that takes a hash
  object as a parameter. The hash object contains parsed pazpar2
  responses (hash members that correspond to the elements in the
  response XML document). Within the handler, the programmer further
  processes the data and updates the viewed document.
 </para>
 <screen>
  function my_onstat(data) {
   var stat = document.getElementById("stat");
   stat.innerHTML = '&lt;span&gt;Active clients: '+ data.activeclients
    + '/' + data.clients + ' | &lt;/span&gt;'
    + '&lt;span&gt;Retrieved records: ' + data.records
    + '/' + data.hits + '&lt;/span&gt;';
  }

  function my_onshow(data) {
   // data contains parsed show response
   for (var i = 0; i &lt; data.hits[0].length; i++)
    // update page with the hits
  }

  function on_record(data) {
   // if detailsstylesheet parameter was set data array
   // will contain raw xml and xsl data
   Element_appendTransformResult(someDiv, data.xmlDoc, data.xslDoc);
  }
 </screen>
 <para><bridgehead><filename>pz2.js</filename> on runtime</bridgehead></para>
 <para>
  The search process is initiated by calling the search method on the
  instantiated pz2 object. To initiate short status reports and
  per-target status information, methods stat and bytarget are
  called accordingly.
 </para>
 <screen>
  my_paz.search (query, recPergPage, 'relevance');
 </screen>
 <para>
  Managing the results (keeping track of the browsed results page and
  sorting) is up to the client's programmer. At any point the show
  method may be called to bring up the latest result set with a
  different sorting criteria or range, without re-executing the
  search on the back-end.
 </para>
 <screen>
  my_paz.show (1, 10, 'relevance');
 </screen>
 <para>
  To retrieve a detailed record, the record command is called. When
  calling the record command, one may temporarily override its default
  callback by specifying the handler parameter. This might be useful
  when retrieving raw records that need to be processed differently.
 </para>
 <screen>
  my_paz.record (recId, 2, 'opac', { “callback”: temp_callback, “args”, caller_args});
 </screen>
 <variablelist>
  <para><bridgehead>PARAMETERS ARRAY</bridgehead></para>
  <varlistentry><term>pazpar2path</term>
  <listitem><para>server path to pazpar2 (relative to the portal). When pazpar2 is installed as a package this does not need to be set. </para></listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term>usesessions</term>
  <listitem><para>Boolean. When set to true <filename>pz2.js</filename> will manage sessions internally, otherwise it is left to the server-side script. Default true.</para></listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term>autoInit</term>
  <listitem><para>Boolean. Sets auto initialization of pazpar2 session on the object instantiation. Default true. Valid only if usesession is set to true.</para></listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term>detailstylesheet</term>
  <listitem><para>path to the xsl presentation stylesheet (relative to the portal) used for the detailed record display</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>errorhandler</term>
  <listitem><para>callback function called on any (pazpar2 or <filename>pz2.js</filename>) internal error</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>oninit</term>
  <listitem><para>specifies init response callback function</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>onstat</term>
  <listitem><para>specifies stat response callback function</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>onshow</term>
  <listitem><para>specifies show response callback function</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>onterm</term>
  <listitem><para>specifies termlist response callback function</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>onrecord</term>
  <listitem><para>specifies record response callback function</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>onbytarget</term>
  <listitem><para>specifies bytarget response callback function</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>onreset</term>
  <listitem><para>specifies reset method callback function</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>termlist</term>
  <listitem><para>comma separated list of facets</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>keepAlive</term>
  <listitem><para>ping period, should not be lower than 5000 usec</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>stattime</term>
  <listitem><para>default 1000 usec</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>termtime</term></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>showtime</term></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>bytargettime</term></varlistentry>

 </variablelist>

 <variablelist>

  <para><bridgehead>METHODS</bridgehead></para>

  <varlistentry><term>stop ()</term>
  <listitem><para>stop activity by clearing timeouts</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>reset ()</term>
  <listitem><para>reset state</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>init (sessionId, serviceId)</term>
  <listitem><para>session-mode, initialize new session or pick up a session already initialized</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>ping ()</term>
  <listitem><para>session-mode, intitialize pinging </para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>search (query, num, sort, filter, showfrom)</term>
  <listitem><para>execute piggy-back search and activate polling on every command specified by assigning command callback (in the pz2 constructor)</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>show (start, num, sort)</term>
  <listitem><para>start or change parameters of polling for a given window of records</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>record (id, offset, syntax, handler)</term>
  <listitem><para>retrieve detailed or raw record. handler temporarily overrides default callback function.</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>termlist ()</term>
  <listitem><para>start polling for termlists</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>bytarget ()</term>
  <listitem><para>start polling for target status</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>stat ()</term>
  <listitem><para>start polling for pazpar2 status</para></listitem></varlistentry>

 </variablelist>

 <para/>
 <para><filename>pz2.js</filename> comes with a set of cross-browser helper classes and functions.</para>

 <variablelist>

  <para><bridgehead>Ajax helper class</bridgehead></para>

  <varlistentry><term>pzHttpRequest</term>
  <listitem><para>a cross-browser Ajax wrapper class</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>constructor (url, errorHandler)</term>
  <listitem><para>create new request for a given url</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>get (params, callback)</term>
  <listitem><para>asynchronous, send the request with given parameters (array) and call callback with response as parameter</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>post (params, data, callback)</term>
  <listitem><para>asynchronous, post arbitrary data (may be XML doc) and call callback with response as parameter</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>load ()</term>
  <listitem><para>synchronous, returns the response for the given request</para></listitem></varlistentry>

 </variablelist>

 <variablelist>

  <para><bridgehead>XML helper functions</bridgehead></para>

  <varlistentry><term>document.newXmlDoc (root)</term>
  <listitem><para>create new XML document with root node as specified in parameter</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>document.parseXmlFromString (xmlString)</term>
  <listitem><para>create new XML document from string</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>document.transformToDoc (xmlDoc, xslDoc)</term>
  <listitem><para>returns new XML document as a result</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>Element_removeFromDoc (DOM_Element)</term>
  <listitem><para>remove element from the document</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>Element_emptyChildren (DOM_Element)</term></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>Element_appendTransformResult (DOM_Element, xmlDoc, xslDoc)</term>
  <listitem><para>append xsl transformation result to a DOM element</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>Element_appendTextNode (DOM_Element, tagName, textContent)</term>
  <listitem><para>append new text node to the element</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>Element_setTextContent (DOM_Element, textContent)</term>
  <listitem><para>set text content of the element</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>Element_getTextContent (DOM_Element)</term>
  <listitem><para>get text content of the element</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>Element_parseChildNodes (DOM_Element)</term>
  <listitem><para>parse all descendants into an associative array</para></listitem></varlistentry>

 </variablelist>

</section>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: nxml
nxml-child-indent: 1
End:
-->
